Guide to the William De Morgan Collection
Yale University Library
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
General Collection of Rare Books and Manuscripts
William De Morgan collection
1886-1913
GEN MSS 141
De Morgan, William Frend, 1839-1917.
3.75 linear feet (9 boxes)
The collection consists of letters and literary manuscripts by William De Morgan. Series I contains letters written to seven acquaintances including T. J. Cobden-Sanderson and William Mozely; some of the topics covered are De Morgan's bicycle patent and a writing project, the inventor John Worrell Keely, and Greek pottery. Series II contains autograph manuscripts and typescripts for four of De Morgan's novels: Joseph Vance (1906), Alice-for-short (1907), It never can happen again (1909), and When ghost meets ghost (1914).
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library P. O. Box 208240 New Haven, CT 06520-8240 Email: beinecke.library@yale.edu Phone: (203) 432-2972 Fax: (203) 432-4047
Administrative Information
Provenance
Collection of material acquired by gift and purchase from various sources between 1938 and 1997. For further information see Collections Contents list.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Description of the Papers
The collection consists of letters and literary manuscripts by William De Morgan. Series I contains letters written to seven acquaintances including T. J. Cobden-Sanderson and William Mozley; some of the topics covered are De Morgan's bicycle patent and a writing project, the inventor John Worrell Keely, and Greek pottery. Series II contains autograph manuscripts and typescripts for four of De Morgan's novels: Joseph Vance (1906), Alice-for-Short (1907), It Never Can Happen Again (1909), and When Ghost Meets Ghost (1914).
William Frend De Morgan (1839-1917)
The artist and author William De Morgan was born on November 16, 1839, the son of Augustus De Morgan (1806-1871), a professor of mathematics at University College, London, and his wife Sophia Frend (1809-1892). De Morgan attended the University College School, London, and the college, after which he studied painting at the Royal Academy Schools from 1859 to 1862. During the 1860s he met the artists William Morris and Edward Burne-Jones, who likely influenced him to turn to the decorative arts: by 1872 De Morgan was living near them in Chelsea and had begun his career as one of the most successful and prominent practitioners of the arts and crafts movement in Britain, known for his innovations in the design and technology of glazes for pottery and tiles. His workshop closed in 1907.
De Morgan began a second career as a novelist while in his sixties. His first book, Joseph Vance: an Ill-Written Autobiography (1906) was a best-seller, which encouraged him to continue writing. His other novels followed in quick succession: Alice-for-Short (1907), Somehow Good (1908), It Never Can Happen Again (1909), An Affair of Dishonour (1909), A Likely Story (1911), and When Ghost Meets Ghost (1914). Two more titles, The Old Madhouse (1917) and The Old Man's Youth (1921), were published posthumously.
In 1887 De Morgan married the painter Evelyn Pickering (1855-1919) and the couple settled in Chelsea at 1, The Vale, Kings Road, where they lived until moving to 127 Church Street in 1910. From the early 1890s through 1914 the De Morgans spent each winter in Florence, Italy, where William De Morgan wrote most of his novels. He died in his home in Chelsea on January 15, 1917.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Letters and Documents, 1886-1913. II. Writings, 1904-1913.
Access Terms
This collection is indexed under the following access points in Orbis, the Yale University Library online catalog.
Subjects
Cobden-Sanderson, T. J. (Thomas James), 1840-1922.; De Morgan, William Frend, 1839-1917.; Keely, John Ernest Worrell, 1827-1898.; Mozley, William E.; Authors, English --20th century --Archives.; English literature --20th century.
Authors
De Morgan, William Frend, 1839-1917.
Collection Contents
- Letters and Documents, 1886-1913; Series I.; 9 folders
  Arranged in two groups: letters filed in alphabetical order by recipient, followed by one folder of cancelled checks.
  The series contains a small group of letters written by William and Evelyn De Morgan from their homes in London and Florence. Subjects are described in each entry below.
  - Letters to Charles A. Aiken, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Library Associates Fund, 1994. Bequest of Harry T. Mercer, Yale 1924 Grad., and Dorothy N. Mercer, for use of the Tinker Library.
    Two autograph letters signed, concerning De Morgan's bicycle patent and possible new bicycle designs; written from Via Lorenzo Magnifico 39, Florence.
    With: autograph letter signed from Evelyn De Morgan to Miss Aiken, 1901 Feb 15
  - Letter to T. J. Cobden-Sanderson, 1906 Oct 8 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Autograph letter signed, concerning mutual friends; written from Chelsea.
    Purchased from Stonehill on the Frank Altschul Fund, 1963.
  - Letter to Mr. Ewing, 1909 Jan 10 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1997.
    Autograph letter signed, in answer to a request for autographs; written from Florence.
  - Letter to Miss Halsey, 1891 Jun 14 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Gift of Halsted B. VanderPoel, 1938.
    Autograph letter signed, concerning John Worrell Keely and his motor; written from 1, The Vale, Kings Road, Chelsea. Removed from William De Morgan, It Never Can Happen Again (London: 1909).
  - Letters to William E. Mozley, 1886-1911 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Three autograph letters signed and two autograph postcards signed, concerning questions about English law "for fiction purposes"; written from Chelsea and Florence.
    With: passport of William E. Mozley, dated 1886 Aug 23.
  - Letter to Miss Sington, 1909 Oct 20 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Autograph letter signed, concerning Miss Sington's request for an autograph; written from 1, The Vale, Kings Road, Chelsea.
    With: autograph note signed, to Miss Moschiler, undated.
    Purchased from David J. Holmes on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1994.
  - Letter to "Dear Madam", 1898 Feb 13 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Autograph letter signed, concerning Greek pottery and glazes; written from Lungo il Mugnone 15, Florence.
  - Cancelled checks (23), 1913 Apr-Jun (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Gift of Fred Bates Johnson, 1954.
- Writings, 1904-1913; Series II.; 3.75 linear feet (9 boxes)
  The series contains manuscripts and typescripts for four of De Morgan's novels, including his first and most famous work, Joseph Vance. Any additional information in the entry was taken from catalogue cards prepared when the material was acquired.
  Arranged in alphabetical order by title.
  - Alice-for-Short
    Purchased from Gabriel Wells on the Library Associates Fund, 1948.
    - Chapters 1-26, autograph manuscript, circa 1906 (Box 1, Folder 9-12)
    - Chapter 22, autograph manuscript, circa 1906 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Volume 2, chapters 1-21, autograph manuscript, circa 1906 (Box 2, Folder 14-16)
  - Alice-for-Short
    Purchased from Maggs Brothers on the Library Associates Fund, 1949.
    - Chapter headings, autograph manuscript, circa 1906 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Chapter 8, autograph manuscript, circa 1906 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      Apparently written after the final manuscript was completed; in the first printed edition of the novel (London, 1907) it was inserted as Chapter 35, which would place it in between chapters 7 and 8 of volume 2 in the manuscript above.
    - Various pages and fragments of pages, with manuscript corrections, additions, and cancellations, circa 1906 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Alice-for-Short
    Gift of Halsted B. VanderPoel, 1951.
    - Typescript with autograph manuscript corrections and additions, circa 1906 (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
    - Typescript with autograph manuscript corrections and additions, circa 1906 (Box 3, Folder 22-28)
  - It Never Can Happen Again
    Ex libris Philip M. Neufeld.
    Purchased from William Reese Co. (Christie's sale, 1995 April 25, Lot 112) on the Chauncey Brewster Tinker Prize Fund, 1995.
    - Chapter outlines, autograph manuscript and typescripts, corrected, circa 1908 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - Chapters 1-27, autograph manuscript, corrected, circa 1908 (Box 4, Folder 30-34)
    - Chapters 28 to end, autograph manuscript, corrected, circa 1908 (Box 5, Folder 35-39)
  - Joseph Vance: an Ill-Written Autobiography
    Purchased from Isaac Mendoza Book Company on the Albert H. Childs Fund, 1957.
    Formerly owned by Mrs. Milton E. Getz.
    - Preface, autograph manuscript, circa 1904 (Box 6, Folder 40)
    - Chapters 1-41, autograph manuscript, circa 1904 (Box 6, Folder 41-47)
    - Chapter 42-Postscript, autograph manuscript, circa 1904 (Box 7, Folder 48-49)
    - Chapters 1-38, typescript with manuscript corrections, circa 1904 (Box 7, Folder 50-53)
    - Chapter 39 to end, typescript with manuscript corrections, circa 1904 (Box 8, Folder 54)
    - Wrapper from manuscript, circa 1904 (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - When Ghost Meets Ghost
    Purchased on the Starling W. Childs Library Fund and Library Associates Funds.
    - Chapters 1-29, autograph manuscript, circa 1913 (Box 8, Folder 56-59)
    - Chapter 30 to end, autograph manuscript, circa 1913 (Box 9, Folder 60-64)
    - Pages withdrawn, autograph manuscript and typescript, corrected, circa 1913 (Box 9, Folder 65)